hello
it is
September 23rd 2022
and we are in meeting four for a cohort
two of the active inference textbook
group
we're having our first discussion of the
chapter two
of the textbook
so
before we
jump to the book and assess where things
are at with questions
does anyone want to provide any
overview thoughts or experiences that
they had like while reading or rereading
chapter two
just overall anything about chapter two
there's a lot of math
okay blue thank you anyone else
okay
we have this questions table and
none have added any questions
specifically for chapter two or if
someone did and put them somewhere else
just let us know
these are really important
we hope and expect and prefer that
people do have questions while they're
reading the text
and this is a really essential learning
practice and it helps improve our
epistemic niche
it also contributes to Future cohorts
and future Learners when we can have
again every single kind of question from
the directly related what does this word
mean here
to the tangential
every kind of question that people have
it's a huge service to actually just add
several of them to this table so we
don't have any for today and that will
free us up to give an overview of
chapter two walk through it and uh kind
of connect a few dots perhaps and then
it'd be awesome in our second discussion
of chapter two
for people to have noted down a few
things that they were curious about
including during this discussion people
can add directly or like write down
somewhere else and add later
um but this is like a really important
way to structure our learning
individually and collectively
so
um
we're going to go into chapter two
and
walk through it
paying attention to the formalisms and
also to a lot of the work that has been
added through the math learning group
and through various people's efforts to
improve the
um
legibility of the math because it'll be
like either
a first coat of paint or a refresher for
truly everyone so everyone's going to be
approaching this and trying to learn the
math
um in different ways
let's start with figure 1.2
this is the high road coming from the
top
and the low road coming from the bottom
chapter 2 is going to be leading with
the low road
chapter 3 is going to be presenting from
The High Road so chapter 2 is going to
begin with an overview of Bayes theorem
Bayesian statistics and then make its
way up through some of these terms
described here
and
reach
that kind of common meeting point with
active inference
before we flip to chapter two does
anyone have any just general comments on
the low road
okay
the chapter begins with this quote from
William James
my thinking is first and last and always
for the sake of my doing
what does anyone think that means or how
does it reflect on them why is it here
anyone can just unmute an address or
raise their hands
Sean
I suppose it's making the connection
between perception and action there with
the thinking and the doing
which is
important in chapter two
awesome
as the name active inference would have
it there are going to be many
connections between
cognition and inference and action like
the embodiment of Maneuvers in the real
embodied world
as well as even ways of thinking about
mental or cognitive behaviors as actions
like attention as action
so that will be a thread that continues
as we continue to build on active
inference
the introduction
paragraph
is first providing a historical View
that even qualitative
and
pre-1900 views
encompassed perception as an unconscious
inference
and as something that was being
generated subliminally and updated and
then kind of presented to awareness
and then
um the author's place the Bayesian brain
hypothesis as a kind of formal
realization of some of those models of
perception and action
and explain how active inference is
going to be extending those ideas by
doing several things
not just considering perception as
unconscious inference
um but also considering various other
cognitive features like action planning
learning
as Bayesian statistical issues in how we
model them
and then by finding approximations
and heuristics
that help us address problems that might
other be otherwise be intractable
um
perception as inference
here the Bayesian brain
perspective is brought up
and does anyone want to like
add anything that they've heard or what
the Bayesian brain kind of
brings up for them
foreign
key feature of the Bayesian brain
that they're going to point to
is
how it contrasts from a kind of outside
in
signal processing purely recognition
based model so we could think of that
model as being descriptive statistics
and also being compatible with frequent
statistics like we're getting kind of a
blurry picture out there and then we're
gonna do um descriptive statistics
frequentism and get some sort of
sharpened realized image like the camera
filter is a little blurry and then we're
just going to post process the image and
that's going to result in the final
image so it's outside in
um
in contrast and this is not novel to
active inference this is being described
as part of the Bayesian brain hypothesis
perceptions not a passive outside in
process
it is a constructive inside out process
in which Sensations are used to confirm
or disconfirm hypothesis about how they
were generative generative
um
the way that that plays out in Bayesian
inference
is with kind of a tale of two densities
density being another name for a
statistical distribution is like a
density
and the tale of two densities was a
paper Title by ramstead at all it was an
early live stream that we did and the
two densities are like the forward and
the reverse model which are used in
Bayesian statistics as well as
expectation maximization and other
algorithms
and here's what those two densities are
there are the density of observations
that's like the observables in the
sensory States and then there's another
density which are like latent States or
hidden states that generate those
observables
so um if we were looking at a red ball
then there'd be like the visual sense
states of the location of the ball and
then there'd be like a hidden stay of
the location of the ball so thermometer
giving us readings of the world and then
the temperature in the room which is an
unobservable
and so we can take thermometer data and
we can use that to fit a temperature
hidden State and also from a given
hidden State we could use a generative
model or what is sometimes referred to
as a forward model
two generate predictions about
observations
in contrast with descriptive statistics
which is taking in observables and kind
of distilling them and then saying well
the mean was 11 and the variance was 4.
if that's the end of the road for that
modeler that's the end of the road but
the Bayesian approach says okay we've
got a mean and a variance
and now we're going to be able to
generate data with mean 11 variance 4.
so that's the tale of two densities is
the way that these two
um generative
processes and a recognition model are
licked
to operationalize that a little bit more
the state of the Hidden variables
a priori
meaning before is called a prior
the prior is then going to be updated by
observations
and depending on a few factors which
we're going to go into
you can imagine one extreme case where
whatever observation comes in you just
instantly update your prior to that so
then it becomes a posterior like after
the fact but the posterior of that first
moment becomes the prior for the next
moment so it's kind of this unfolding
process
and again one extreme case would be
whatever comes in from the world you
just instantly update your prior to that
so that's like a zero memory just
instantly updating to that incoming data
point like what's the average height in
this classroom well this child was four
feet tall okay the average is four now
there's five feet okay now it's five
feet tall
The Other Extreme would be like
very much denoising the observations by
having a really stable maybe even
stubborn hidden State estimate
this relates also to attention because
when we pay attention to observables we
update our priors more when we're not
paying attention observables coming in
don't update our hidden State estimates
Bayes rule tells us how to combine
different elements the prior and the
likelihood
such that a prior probability becomes
transformed into a posterior probability
so you have some a priori estimate of
How likely it is to be raining at that
moment
then you're going to detect
wetness on your skin or not
and then there's going to be a posterior
probability update
Bayesian inference is a broad topic
and so there's many resources in place
to learn but it's also very important
thing to know in active inference
box 2.1
covers some of the underlying mechanics
of
Bayes theorem
um which is like very simple and taught
logical
yet very powerful in its application
there's an example introduced here
that's going to come up several more
times in the book
and does anyone want to like explain
this
example
with the frogs and the apples like what
is happening here
so the situation is that there's a
person holding something in their hands
and there's only two options for what it
could be either a frog or an apple
they also this is their prior belief
there's a 10 chance that it's a frog 0.1
because we scale probability
distributions to like a total of one
because something must happen
but a one for a statistical distribution
is like a hundred percent
so there's a 10 chance of it being a
frog and a 90 chance of what they're
holding being an apple a priori that's
their prior
then they have some sort of likelihood
model the likelihood model describes for
apples and for frogs
how different actions are emitted by
them so apples jump one percent of the
time that's the probability of action
equals jumping vertical line means
conditioned upon
so the probability of jumping
conditioned upon the hidden State being
an apple is one percent
the probability of no jump conditioned
on an Apple being the hidden state is 99
so apples rarely jump
in contrast the probability of jumping
observing a jump when the hidden state
is a frog is 81 percent and 19 for not
jumping
so a priori
there's a 10 percent belief that it's a
frog ninety percent that it's an apple
that's representing the uncertainty
around what the object is
then a jump is observed
just intuitively even without any
equations
if we know that frogs are more likely to
jump than Apples observing a jump
should increase our favor
of that being like a jumping object and
so that's exactly what happens and
that's what the Bayesian
statistics describe is a situation where
you have a prior belief about hidden
States
that are not directly observable
and you have a likelihood model of how
observables which is here why
how observables map to different hidden
States and then through the observations
you update and realize a posterior
belief about hidden States
does anyone have any thoughts or
questions about this
we're going to continue on the low road
this
is a method called exact base
so this is kind of like a plug and chug
method
where you can take what is described in
box one
and apply it to the values that are
presented here
and you get the exact calculation of
different variables depending on what
you're trying to find you're going to be
able to calculate basically every
variable every unknown you can kind of
isolate for and solve
um this is called exact base
exact base
has
um
a clear
intuition
for small state spaces so when it's like
there's two options there's two for
hidden State and two options for
Behavior it's quite easy to calculate
for large State spaces it becomes or
unknown State spaces it can become
intractable so that's going to motivate
some of the heuristics that are brought
in later
um
okay
table two again people can just please
raise your hands if you have any
thoughts or questions or want to like
dwell on it at a part
table 2.1
is going to be uh Brock yes
I just wanted to if anyone is feeling
like
um so blue
is she said there's a lot of math in
this chapter
and um
she's one of the co-workers so that the
prince Institute and I'm um this is my
second time through so
um if you're feeling like this is a lot
of math you're not alone but that's okay
um
I I just I don't know just wanted to say
that like it's it
I think
the way this is presented here is really
helpful for people that have a grasp on
some of the other
um
even simpler Parts like the way that you
made this distinction of between the
generative model being a thing that's
producing predictions and the like
that's a really important thing to
understand
um the Bayesian brain versus this sort
of bottom-up
um
um predictive sort of machine thing
part of what is happening there though
that I guess we're gonna get into a
little bit more when he's talking about
hidden State spaces is that um like what
what that all depends on
when he's going through this apple and
frog example is that there's
um
a conditional probability here that like
the reason that you believe that the
frog is jumping or whatever or not or
might jump is because it's a frog
and that may seem like
well
obviously or like so what like that you
know but if it's something a little uh
less you know I don't know contrived or
something like
um what is Brock gonna say next or
whatever
like then
it helps maybe to have more priors on
what what I'm you know and what uh
I generally say you know so I I guess
what I'm saying I'm trying to draw some
attention to those conditional
probability it's um
kind of uh
like a simple concept but it's kind of
what makes that whole thing work at all
is that there are probabilities that are
kind of like
strongly related and it may be part of a
hidden state or whatever
um but that's kind of what is
if there weren't any conditional
probabilities none of this would work
um
and that's kind of the uh the magic
simple Secret Sauce there that's that's
getting traction on so
that's
helpful or more confusing but
thanks for the comments uh the personal
comments Brock and also yes the
conditional probability this vertical
line
does so much what's the probability that
the Giants win against the Yankees
well in my view it's 50 no conditional
upon it raining
maybe that doesn't matter in your
generative model conditional upon this
what if I told you that it was seven
nothing in the third inning
like
all these situations where information
comes in and there's information that
doesn't update our prior
like if you uh give a piece of
irrelevant information then it doesn't
update our prior so like conditioned
upon the irrelevant information
then we're not updating our hidden State
estimate
whereas there's other information that
comes in that is relevant and that's
going to have to do with the sparsity of
how the variables are connected and then
those conditional estimates help us
reduce our uncertainty
what's the overall probability that
somebody has this has a medical degree
in the world it's just the number of
medical degrees in the world divided by
the total population of the world
conditioned upon being in this situation
what is it and so that can be a
different number
um
table two one gives a little bit of a
statistical detail on several different
forms of distributions now again even
for people who have taken several
courses or even years of Statistics
these are not trivial Concepts
the piece though that we'll just
highlight is what a support means and
what surprise means support is
describing where that distribution
is even valid or definable
so there's some distributions like the
gaussian that have support
over all real numbers that's what the
fancy R means so like a gaussian the
kind of archetypal case is it's a bell
curve centered at zero and it goes off
to Infinity in both directions with
vanishingly small numbers but it has
support everywhere so that's the
gaussian
um in contrast there's other
distribution families
that for example can only exist on the
range between like zero and infinity
so that would be like waiting time
between events
it can't be a negative number so the
gaussian is like an inappropriate
distribution of family
to even describe situations that can't
be negative
surprise is a formula
that for any given observation
helps you determine how surprising that
data point is so we have the children in
the classroom and the average height is
four feet plus or minus one foot
and we observe
a new measurement and it's exactly four
feet
that is like the least surprising
observation possible
and then as it gets further away from
four like the standard deviation
increases
it's more surprising
and so these
formula
describe for each distribution family
how to calculate surprise so that's just
the surprise how surprising a new data
point coming in is
observation
given the Observer given the hidden
States as they're estimated
um okay so that's one notion of surprise
that's kind of like new data point comes
in
how surprising is it
there's a second notion of surprise
that's called Bayesian surprise
Bayesian surprise is how much your prior
moves
following an observation
so you could imagine again we have a
four foot estimate for the average
classroom
and data points are coming in and we're
surprised or not
that's regular surprise
Bayesian surprise
is the difference between the prior and
the posterior
so we could get seven foot measurements
again and again and again and again
but because we're super stubborn in our
prior
we're still keeping that four foot
estimate
so those data points are surprising
surprising surprising surprising but the
Bayesian surprise is zero because the
prior is not being updated into a new or
different posterior
um
that's a little bit on the difference
between
vanilla surprise naked surprise
and Bayesian surprise this is
specifically within the Bayesian
statistics updating framework
how do we how do we quantify surprise
well we have these formulas you just
plug in like the observation and some of
the parameters of the distribution the
parameters are like the values that make
the distribution the way it is so for a
gaussian there's two parameters like
mean and variance
where's the mean of the bell curve the
average and how wide is the bell curve
those are parameters surprise can be
calculated from the parameters of the
distribution and the observation
with these equations
how do we calculate Bayesian surprise
this is going to introduce an operation
that may be familiar to some or not but
it's it's all good it's called the KL
Divergence callback Library Divergence
and
this is what it looks like
again these are topics where one can go
very very deep and learn a lot so just
treat it like many coats of paint
you're going to know it's a KL
Divergence because it's dkl
just like if it was like f of x is like
a function of x
d k l brackets means that we're going to
be talking about a KL Divergence
about what's in the square brackets
so at this point I'm going to go over
the equations
I'm going to find equation 2.3
so we can see it here I'm also going to
open up
the description
so this is really helpful this is a
super important and valuable
contribution for people who can
to create natural language descriptions
of equations
because it helps get us all on the same
page because otherwise this is like
inscrutable again even for people who
might know the area because the notation
can be slightly different with different
letters like what is Q and so on
um so the KL Divergence
is going to be hinging upon these two
vertical lines
when it's one vertical line
it's going to be used in a lot of
different statistic situations to mean
conditional upon x x line Y X
conditioned on y
the two vertical lines
are going to be what the KL Divergence
is being calculated between
so this is describing the KL Divergence
between the Q and the P distribution
here's Q of X this is a function
here's P of X that's a function
um
specifically for Bayesian surprise we're
talking about the KL Divergence between
the prior and the posterior
so the KL Divergence between the prior
probability distribution Q of X and the
posterior probability distribution P of
x
and then the second part here
what does that mean
equal sign with a triangle
is by definition
that's what the triangle means on top
is the expectation
that's fancy e
means expectation over so it's the
average value of
Q of x
of
the natural log
of Q minus natural log of P this part's
a little bit less important a little bit
more detail but this is where we're
going to see it mostly written out as
with two vertical lines and the kale
Divergence is measuring the difference
between them if they're the same
distribution
the difference is zero if they're very
different the value is going to be high
it's kind of like how much Earth do you
have to move
to reshape the distributions to look
like each other
it's not exactly that but that's kind of
what a KL Divergence is
so
here we can think about the Bayesian
surprise of that frog Jumping Brook yes
um I was just gonna say I guess this
those details I think this natural log
of Q of x minus July
that
um another way to say that is that
that's information
those are uh mats or
like a form of bits kind of
um so that's the expected
difference of information is there zero
information or is there
some change in other words between the
the the P of X being the um prior and
the Q of X being
uh so
that
Divergence when he's about to go into
his his
that's what we're talking about is like
how much space is there informationally
between those two things
great so anat
is a unit of measurement for information
a bit is a binary bit that's zero one
digital computers use bits so people are
pretty familiar sometimes with a bit
a Nat is a unit that's not based around
zero one it's based around the natural
log and base e
instead of like a base 2 binary system
so it's monotonically related to bits
which is to say like they're both going
to go up and they're both going to go
down but they're not exactly comparable
it's like inches and feet
um
here when we were calculating just
regular surprise so how surprising the
observation is
that could be calculated in Nets
was it a surprising observation or not
did it did it surprise me at all that
that can be calculated about surprise
here
knots are also used to calculate the
informational Divergence between the
prior and the posterior when we're
thinking about Bayesian surprise
box 2.2
introduces the fancy e notation
fancy e is standing for expectation
now sometimes conversationally
expectation is talking about the future
like what do you expect the weather to
be tomorrow
in the statistical sense
expectation
is
the average expected value
it doesn't necessarily refer to the
Future
it could be an expectation about a
future time point
but also
alone
it is only describing basically the
average of a distribution
the expectation of a gaussian is the
center of the bell curve not like what
one believes it's going to be in the
future but if someone said what is the
expectation
for of your in your model for what the
average is going to be in 10 time steps
that can be addressed so it's compatible
with the way that people talk about what
do you expect to happen tomorrow
but just be aware that expectation alone
does not refer necessarily to a future
time point it's just referring to a
statistical average
and
um One Note again may be familiar to
some maybe the first time hearing for
some
but it's going to come into play in this
book is there are discrete State spaces
and continuous State spaces a discrete
State space is one where values can only
take certain like clickable values like
0 1 2 3 4 or it could be
0.1.2.3.4 but it's like there are
discrete values on a grid that can be
achieved
like the two options for what the thing
in the hand was it's a discrete State
space whether it's two or two million
it's a finite set
of definables and there's no in-betweets
in contrast continuous State spaces
would be like a continuous variable
describing the temperature
now one could also Describe temperature
with a discrete State space in my model
I'm describing temperature as either 20
21 22 23 only integer values are allowed
for my model
there's advantages
and there's challenges for both discrete
and continuous State spaces
and this book is going to be like
juxtaposing them and the chapters even
later are going to be like kind of
alternating between them
because there's active inference in
discrete situations discrete State
spaces discrete time and then there's
also active inference in continuous
State spaces and continuous time
so
that was very low down on the low road
nothing of the above was like about
active inference or even many of the
ideas that often bring people to the
table that was kind of like an overview
on some Bayesian statistical ideas
Bronwyn
this goes back a little bit though I
just wanted to maybe ask these questions
before we move on
one was um in relation to conditional
probability or the the role of
conditions I think Brock sort of talked
to it a little bit
um
is it is that with the conditional thing
like you know in Melbourne tomorrow
there's the Grand Final so you know
you've got two teams
and you said you know there's a 50 50
chance but it depends on what
what conditions
uh those conditions
are they mostly subjective I mean they
can be subjective
and they can be factual as well so
um yeah I suppose it's the question is
um the condition what what states are
the conditions are there they can they
both be well they mostly subject
subjective or can you have the fact that
frogs jump
as as that's what frog frogs do so that
that's what generally happens so that's
not really my subjective
uh opinion of frogs
but does my subjective opinion puts a
condition
honors does that make sense yeah great
question
these models in their Construction
like what their overall structure is and
then in their parameterization like what
the values are are subjective they're
modeler dependent
and so we might have different
perspectives on the overall likelihood
of one team to win
and then somebody might say it's going
to rain tomorrow or it is raining now
and then in your model you had that
that's a gonna update your prior but
maybe it doesn't update my prior so it
is even when it's like frustratingly
obvious it is still also subjective and
multi-perspectival
okay great
that's what I thought and then that
leads on to to the Bayesian surprise the
two differences between surprise and
Bayesian surprise
and that
how Bayesian surprise actually operates
in the world say in relationship
to that like I might say geelong's going
to win tomorrow and even when they're
lost I still think they've won
um and you can't you can't um
convince me of anything other than that
is that where my prior doesn't change
um
yeah so how does base in Surprise itself
well can you give us some examples of
how that might operate in in the world
in the real world
yeah it's an awesome question and to
connect really
surprised by itself so how surprising a
single observation is independent of how
it changes your belief
um you have a stereotype about some sort
of situation
something surprising happens but then
the Bayesian surprises zero because it's
a recalcitrant belief that the person
has
yeah in contrast there might be a
surprising event that induces a Bayesian
surprise because someone's like whoa I
thought about it this way and then I was
surprised by this observation and that
brought me over here
and then neither of those are the
experience of surprise
but that's an area of a lot of research
and discussion which is like how did
these Concepts in statistics like
beliefs surprises preferences
how do those map onto our psychology and
phenomenology is a preference in active
inference like I prefer A over B
is a expectation
related to what people use every day and
that's kind of the fun part with the
active inference ontology is some of
these terms are not used in day-to-day
conversation and so it's like a blank
campus but in other situations these are
terms that are used
day-to-day ambiguity yeah attention
belief
and so are we using them in a technical
sense that's compatible or isomorphic
with the way that it's used broadly
is incompatible
and so on
that's that's interesting I just had a
different perception of Bayesian
surprise then when you said surprise is
always surprise
but
Beijing surprise maps on to I think you
said something like the psychology or
the preferences or or whatever so so
it's not it's not really a surprise it's
it's how we
um manage surprise
could it be like that that's how what
sort of precisions we have on things so
that we so that we recognize something
or we don't recognize it
is it something like that excellent and
the connection to Precision is also
technically correct which is that when
observations are coming in and we're
treating them precisely
we do have Bayesian surprise because we
are updating our priors
when we have imprecision about
observations we do not update our
distributions of beliefs like oh that's
just a bad thermometer I know it says
that I believe it's 37 in the room
the thermometer is just weird it says 65
but don't worry about it
so then that's a surprising observation
under the belief that it's 37 plus or
minus one
but it doesn't induce a Bayesian
surprise because we haven't updated our
prior
prior yeah okay that's interesting
yep awesome so just to kind of so let's
yeah continue please
uh it's also interesting in that um I
watched that um
the the
um the podcasting with uh John for
record
um
the other day and it was interesting out
of there that just the language the use
of language and then you were just
talking about the ontology and different
uses and are we actually considering the
words that we're hearing
as as they actually are I think that's
really yeah it's really interesting
area with all of this because and it
makes it really
what I've noticed in my in in what I
listen to and and my studies is that
it's like you have to keep going over
and over and over until someone says
something like you just said then
okay
incredible
thank you
that's the relevance realization in a
way with language
just looks interesting oh
sorry
it is interesting
um so we pay attention to it we update
our priors we learn
and we deal with the surprising
observations and we deal with the
Bayesian surprise to adjust our regime
of attention and action
along all these ways
and
we Meme and connect with the active
phonetology
rather than spiraling off into
um uncertainties that aren't relevant
but that's not to banish uncertainty
like from the realm
it's to have the right core screenings
that help us deal with certain features
of action and perception
um
here here's the subjective questions
coming up Bayesian inference is optimal
and this is also the root of like a
million discussions how can it be
optimal to to crash a car how could it
be optimal to be wrong I mean we were
talking about the how could I how could
I be wrong if betting is always optimal
how could I be wrong
inference is subjective
the results are not necessarily active
accurate in any objective sense
Bayesian cognition
and optimal Bayesian calculation again
doesn't mean Society accepts that
neurodiversity
it means that given that person's
generative model and the observations
coming in
or their body as an embody generative
model and the observations and
constraints coming in
that is its own local optimality and
then there's secondary discussions
around like is it adequate is it
um best amongst a family of
counterfactuals does society accept that
and those are discussions to have but
that's irrational
will not be found here
and that's a very interesting angle that
kind of reframes a lot of again
rationality versus irrational thinking
um
yeah and this is a second reason for
optimality being thought of as
subjective okay here we're going to get
to figure two two
which is a schematic that's going to be
very
um different remixes of this schematic
will be found
in many places
um
here is our model of temperature in the
world
here's the real temperature in the world
hidden state
here's our thermometer
observations coming in
we're updating and then we're taking
actions which may
over you know in some way influence the
state of the temperature in the room
so this is like the cybernetic Loop this
is the control theoretic Loop
this is describing
um a kind of generalized again not
active inference unique way
in which
um cognitive entities
take in observations
juxtapose them with a generative model
and then do action selection to
influence the hidden States
such that the observations are brought
into alignment with their preferences
among other things
um
here's a short discussion that the state
spaces don't have to be the same
between x and x star
so temperature in the real world might
be like a continuous variable
whereas we might just have a binary
state is it too hot or not too hot
or you might have a three state too cold
just right too hot or five states
getting too hot actually
and then you might want to do model
selection across two three four five
states internally
and none of that hinges on quote how it
really is
so
um there's a lot of degrees of freedom
in generating cognitive models
and their structure doesn't need to map
on to the neural anatomy of the brain it
doesn't need to map onto a physical
mechanism about the cognitive system
which you may or may not even know and
it doesn't have to be isomorphic the
same structure as the hidden states of
the world
okay
all of this so far has been purely
inferential Brock
I just wanted to I don't know leave a
bookmark here uh stigmatically
um
that you mentioned something about
neurodiversity there in the uh context
of the Bayes optimality
Rabbit Hole
um and um just wanted to remind that
like the origins of this come from
uh Psychiatry and or the impetus for it
of trying to have a
causal reasoning tool for addressing
certain kinds of
mental illnesses so it's it really
it doesn't yeah it just like you said it
doesn't have to map to a specific you
know architecture of brain Arrangement
it's this in the world or whatever it's
you know it is very much like
based on the subjective model that's
already in there
and um
it it could
you could
seeing the whole thing perhaps like
reason about how it might make sense
from their perspective
for
many different kinds of priors or
whatever and um
and why that would be optimal
for that model like or seem like at this
yeah so
great comments and to kind of just
Force age chapter nine
this is the metabasian so it's
the modeler's subjective model
the psychiatrist's subjective model of
their partner's subjective model
so that is the um Genesis of so many
discussions around the map and the
territory and the fallacies and the
fallacies upon fallacies and the the
cause and effect and all these different
discussions
and this is how this modeling framework
wraps that up it's a subjective model of
a subjective model
and that double subjectivity opens up an
unbelievable amount of degrees of
freedom in modeling
which then refocuses the imperative
towards selecting from these models
but that's a little bit of a later point
um
just to in in the last minutes because
again next week hopefully
um many people will add
simple tangential Advanced formal any
kind of questions
um but let's just in the last three or
four minutes just see what else is going
to happen
all of this up to the point has been
inferential Bayesian brain
#livestream 43
they're going to extend that inference
about temperature
so to speak
in to include action
how that happens
is
at the heart of active inference
in the next sections they're going to
clarify the quantity that active
inference agents minimize through
perception action as variational free
energy one note minimization and
maximization are like twins of each
other because with just a negative sign
they can be the same so when you see
minimization or maximization you can
just think of like finding
relatively
higher or lower values
but like whether you choose to think of
um like biologists talk about climbing
mounts improbable like a Dawkins book
and a physicist might talk about finding
the bottom of an energy well
but those are like going to be seen as
kind of
um
not even like just sisters or twins of
each other but like they're actually
kind of the same thing through a
negative sign
there's two ways to reduce free energy
as we will all come to learn and love
you can update your model that's
learning and perception
and you can act in the world that's
action action and inference active
inference
first you can learn
this is a variant of figure 2-2
where now we're being able to see how
the prediction and the observation are
being
put together
there's some discrepancy
in any realistic situation there will
eventually be a discrepancy
and then here are those two roads to
reduce free energy change beliefs
which can be perception perception and
learning are much more similar in active
inference than other Frameworks
like when the ball moves across your
visual field are you perceiving it or
are you learning the position of it as
it moves over rapid time skills so
they're kind of the same
and can you act
here's how you can resolve that
discrepancy you can change your mind
about what you're seeing that's
perception
or you could act
that doesn't mean both of them are
equally good or they're going to result
in your survival or they're plausible in
any given situation so it's always
situational what affordances
there are for Learning and perception
and for action but this is the general
framework
how does free energy get Quantified and
minimized
we'll return to this later but equation
2 5 and 2 6 are going to be really key
equations
thankfully through the work of of many
people here
we have really excellent natural
language descriptions connected to the
ontology
we also have a lot of like notes and
questions people have added
and things like derivations
for those who want to go that way that
Jacob and others have worked on
so
these lines of symbols
can be read this way and with a mouse
over
we can see what those are so yes it's
like words words words
but um we we have a staged development
around these equations because we're
going to be revisiting them and
understanding how this F
as the free energy that's being
minimized I mean free energy principle
this is kind of what it's about
how can it be
decomposed
into these different
sets of natural language terms and in
what sense are these terms being used
again we don't have the minutes to
describe but variational free energy f
is about the past of the presence
that's figures I mean equation two five
equation
um and this is what it looks like a
little bit graphically
here's variational free energy
the same figure that was two before but
now there's an equation here
when we want to look into the future
there are going to be several
complexities arising which is that we're
talking about the surprise of
observations we haven't observed yet and
we're talking about the consequences of
actions that we aren't sure about what
their consequences will be and so
variational free energy F equation 2.5
morphs into expected free energy G
equation 2.6
similarly
excellent work in progress as everything
is to unpack what this is in natural
language
there are some special cases for
expected free energy
such that when certain terms are ignored
or set to zero we get a lot of special
cases
that are in quite broad use
and then that's the end of the low road
equation 2 5 variational free energy
past and present equation 2 6 expected
free energy G
future
that's the end of the low road chapter
so
that has been this first discussion on
chapter two
hope that people have enjoyed and it
would be extremely appreciated to write
any questions that you have on chapter
two
so that we can as as people were adding
during this conversation so that we can
have some specifics to follow up on so
good luck with your learning in the next
week and see you all soon